

Hunter Ratliff

Nuclear Engineer, Researcher, Code Developer

27 years old

Tokai, Ibaraki, Japan

available upon request

hratliff.com

contact@hratliff.com

in linkedin.com/in/hunter-ratliff

United States citizenship

Skills -

Languages

English

Japanese

Programming

Python, Jupyter Fortran (IV/77/90/08) **MATLAB**

C++

CMD/Bash scripting

JavaScript, Brython Git, GitHub

Nuclear / Scientific

MCNP6/X/5, PHITS ROOT

SCALE/ORIGEN

Geant4

Other

LaTeX, TikZ, MetaPost • Microsoft Office Suite

Windows local systems • Unix remote systems

HTML, CSS, Markdown • •

Summary

Hunter is a researcher with an education in nuclear engineering whose experience is predominantly with cosmic-ray-like ion accelerator experiments, analysis and visualization of large experimental and modeled datasets, radiation transport simulations using MCNP and PHITS, space radiation modeling, activation and decay calculations, and code development in Python and Fortran. He also has interests in radiotherapy, radiation protection and shielding, and radioisotope production.

Experience

Apr. 2019 present

Postdoctoral Fellow

Japan Atomic Energy Agency (JAEA)

Member of the PHITS particle transport code development team, serving as the current lead developer of the DCHAIN-PHITS activation, buildup, burnup, and decay code coupled to and distributed alongside PHITS. Implemented modern decay and cross section libraries, uncertainty propagation, reaction tracking, tetrahedral and 3-D grid mesh geometry support, performance improvements, new input/output features, and more into DCHAIN. Authored the user guide/manual and assists with user support for DCHAIN-PHITS.

May 2015 -Feb. 2019

Graduate Research Assistant The University of Tennessee, Knoxville

Conducted accelerator experiments emulating radiation conditions within spacecraft, characterized resulting neutron spectra, and modeled the experiments in MCNP. Other projects included modeling the Martian surface's radiation environment from galactic cosmic rays and solar particle events in MCNP and PHITS and modernizing the

CLSQ Fortran IV decay analysis code in Python.

Aug. 2015 -Dec. 2016

Graduate Teaching Assistant The University of Tennessee, Knoxville Lead laboratory experience portions of courses within the Nuclear

Engineering Department, further developing skills in troubleshooting radiation detectors and associated pulse chain equipment, teaching, communication, and providing constructive guidance to students.

May 2014 -Aug. 2014

Engineering Student Intern

Oak Ridge National Laboratory

Ran, debugged, and composed documentation for an in-house computational fluid dynamics code written in C++ and Fortran.

Education

May 2015 -

Dec. 2018 Grade: A (4.0/4.0) Ph.D. in Nuclear Engineering

The University of Tennessee, Knoxville

Organized, conducted, and analyzed data from 400 hours of beam experiments at the NASA Space Radiation Laboratory in Brookhaven National Laboratory, characterizing the neutron environment within (emulated) spacecraft bombarded by cosmic rays using established time-of-flight and newly developed deconvolution techniques. This required substantial scripting to filter and process the raw data into spectra and to generate, run, and process MCNPX/6 models of the experiment. Further detailed dose analyses were explored to draw conclusions on optimal spacecraft shielding materials, thicknesses, and configurations to minimize risk to astronauts.

May 2015 -Dec. 2016 Grade: A (4.0/4.0)

0 0 0

M.S. in Nuclear Engineering

The University of Tennessee, Knoxville Designed and conducted MCNP6 simulations of the galactic cosmic ray-induced radiation environment on the Martian surface, modeling

the individual particle spectra and dosimetric data as seen by the Radiation Assessment Detector onboard the Mars Curiosity Rover.

Aug. 2011 -May 2015 Grade: A (3.94/4.0) **B.S.** in Nuclear Engineering

The University of Tennessee, Knoxville Designed a plate-fuel research reactor relevant to nuclear propulsion

fuels testing and modeled its criticality and shielding in MCNP for a proposed critical experiment facility as a final design project.

Hunter Ratliff

Nuclear Engineer, Researcher, Code Developer

Specialties

Programming and scripting

Monte Carlo methods/simulation

Data analysis and visualization

Documentation and presentation

Nuclear data processing/formatting

Web design/online tool development

Professional Bio

Hunter studied nuclear engineering at the University of Tennessee from 2011 to 2015 at an undergraduate level and, when presented with very interesting space radiation research opportunities, continued on with his graduate studies at UTK, graduating at the end of 2018. Afterward, he moved to Japan in early 2019 to join the PHITS code development team at the Japan Atomic Energy Agency.

Personal Bio

After living his entire life in the US state of Tennessee, Hunter made his first trip abroad: moving to Japan. Since, he has thoroughly enjoyed exploring the local scenery, culture, and language. New experiences in travel, cuisine, and forces of nature (earthquakes) have truly opened his eyes to the staggering variety of experiences the world has to offer. He is enthusiastic about learning other languages and cultures on his now-international journey through life.

Other -



American Nuclear Society member

Tennessee Class D driver's license

Eagle Scout, Boy Scouts of America

Degrees, certificates, and any other documents available upon request

Selected Publications (full list: hratliff.com/publications/)

2021 Development of scalable deconvolution methods for determining secondary target neutron yields from dual-thick-target cosmic-ray ion accelerator experiments

H.N. Ratliff, N.A. McGirl, M.R. Beach, L.A. Castellanos, M.S. Clowdsley, L.H. Heilbronn, C. La Tessa, J.W. Norbury, A. Rusek, M. Sivertz, A.P.

Srikrishna, H. Wang, and C. Zeitlin

Nucl. Instrum. Methods Phys. Res., B, (in internal review)

Double-differential primary target neutron yields from dual-thicktarget proton and heavy ion accelerator experiments

H.N. Ratliff, N.A. McGirl, M.R. Beach, L.A. Castellanos, M.S. Clowdsley, L.H. Heilbronn, C. La Tessa, J.W. Norbury, A. Rusek, M. Sivertz, A.P.

Srikrishna, H. Wang, and C. Zeitlin

Nucl. Instrum. Methods Phys. Res., B, (in internal review)

2020 Modernization of the DCHAIN-PHITS activation code with new fea-

tures and updated data libraries

<u>H.N. Ratliff</u>, N. Matsuda, S. Abe, T. Miura, T. Furuta, Y. Iwamoto, T. Sato Nucl. Instrum. Methods Phys. Res., B, 484, 29–41, Dec. 2020.

2017 Simulation of the GCR spectrum in the Mars Curiosity Rover's RAD

detector using MCNP6

H.N. Ratliff, M.B.R. Smith, and L.H. Heilbronn

Life Sciences in Space Research, 14, Suppl. C, 43–50, Jun. 2017.

The radiation environment on the surface of Mars - Summary of

model calculations and comparison to RAD data

D. Matthiä, D.M. Hassler, W. de Wet, B. Ehresmann, A. Firan, J. Flores-McLaughlin, J. Guo, L.H. Heilbronn, K. Lee, <u>H.N. Ratliff</u>, R.R. Rios, T. Slaba, M.B.R. Smith, L.W. Townsend, T. Berger, G. Reitz, R.F. Wimmer-

Schweingruber, and C. Zeitlin

Life Sciences in Space Research, 14, Suppl. C, 18–28, Jun. 2017.

Honors and Awards

2015 – 2018	Chancellor's Distinguished Graduate Fellowship	Univ. of Tennessee
2011 – 2015	Chancellor's Honors Program	Univ. of Tennessee
2013 – 2014	Eastland Family Engineering Scholarship	
2013	US Nuclear Regulatory Commission Scholarship	
2012 – 2013	Energy Solutions Corporation Engineering Scholarsl	nip

Hobbies

2021

Coding Leveraging the power of scripting to automate everyday tasks like

resizing desktop wallpapers to a desired aspect ratio, managing file

properties, backing up data, and more.

2011 – 2012 Tennessee Society of Professional Engineers Scholarship

Web design Constructing and tinkering with his personal website hratliff.com,

custom HTML browser new tab page, and online-accessible interac-

tive Jupyter notebooks with scientific applications.

Mixology Responsibly exploring the diverse world of cocktails and mixed drinks,

learning about the history of the ingredients and many recipes.

Edutainment Watching educational documentaries and videos on a wide variety of

topics including geography, mountaineering, exploration, technology, construction, engineering, linguistics, wood/metalworking, business, geopolitics, travel, chemistry, mathematics, food, and history.

References

available upon request

March 6, 2021 Hunter Ratliff